<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The sea fight in the Road of Gibraltar the 25. of Aprill last, betwixt the K. of Spaines carackts and gallions, and the Hollandish men of warre, reported by a letter written a-bourd the Hollands fleete, by a commaunder in the same, and faithfully translated into English</title>
            <title>Copye van een brief, geschreven door Joris van Spelbergh. English</title>
            <author>Spilbergen, Joris van, 1568?-1620.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1607</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 12 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11246</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21507</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116312</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851529</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851529</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16806</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11246)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16806)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 723:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The sea fight in the Road of Gibraltar the 25. of Aprill last, betwixt the K. of Spaines carackts and gallions, and the Hollandish men of warre, reported by a letter written a-bourd the Hollands fleete, by a commaunder in the same, and faithfully translated into English</title>
                  <title>Copye van een brief, geschreven door Joris van Spelbergh. English</title>
                  <author>Spilbergen, Joris van, 1568?-1620.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by John Windet] for Iohn Hardie, and are to be sold by Robert Iackson, at the shop vnder the Royall Exchaunge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1607.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: I.V.S.</note>
                  <note>Probably a translation of "Copye van een brief, geschreven door Joris van Spelbergh [i.e. Spilbergen]"  (Knuttel 1372). See also, however, Knuttel 1357, 1358, 1370, and 1371.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>With a title-page woodcut.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf and the last leaf are blank.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The Spanish ouerthrow at sea by the Hollanders.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Naval battles --  Gibraltar --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16806:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16806:1"/>
            <p>THE SEA FIGHT IN the Road of Gibraltar the 25. <hi>of Aprill laſt, betwixt the K. of</hi> Spaines Carackts and Gallions, and the Hollandiſh men of Warre, reported by a letter written a-bourd the Hollands Fleete, by a commaunder in the ſame, and faithfully tranſlated into Engliſh,</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of ship</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>¶ London printed for <hi>Iohn Hardie,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Robert Jackſon,</hi> at the ſhop vnder the Royall Exchaunge 1607.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:16806:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16806:2"/>
            <head>A COPIE OF A LET<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter written out of the Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors <hi>Fleet at ſea, the fourth</hi> of May. 1607. <hi>Stilo Nouo tranſlated.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing vnder the hight of 36. degrees, or afore the riuer of <hi>Liſbone</hi> vpon the tenth of Aprill. our Admirall <hi>Iacob Van Hemſterk</hi> and his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell determined and fully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued, to enter into the ſaid riuer withall our ſhippes to aſſaile and ſpoile the Caracts &amp; Gallyons lying there, but being cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely aduertiſed that the Carackts were gon and that the Gallyons being 8. or 9. were wholy vnrigged &amp; their ordinance on ſhoare, ſo as it would bee two monthes before they could bee ready, the aforeſaid reſolution was for that time ſtaied; &amp; the rather for that diuers Engliſh and French ſhippes comming out of Saint <hi>Lucar</hi> &amp; <hi>Cales,</hi> brought vs certaine newes that not long before their comming forth, fifteene Spaniſh
<pb facs="tcp:16806:3"/>
ſhippes of warre of Saint <hi>Lucar</hi> and <hi>Cales,</hi> had put to ſea and were gone to the ſtraights of <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braltar,</hi> being eleuen Gallions and the reſt ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler merchants ſhips as then made men of war: Whereupon we reſolued to follow and finde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out, but the winde being at Eaſt, wee met a Floſhinger called <hi>Loy Sailemaker</hi> that came out of the ſtraights the 22. of Aprill and ſhewed vs that the night before hee had beene in companie with the Spaniſh fleete, and that in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning finding himſelfe alone without company, hee ſuppoſed they had taken their courſe for <hi>Cales</hi> for with an eaſterlie winde they might come out of the ſtraights. Vpon the 24. of Aprill the winde comming weſterly wee paſt cloſe by the barre of Saint <hi>Lucar</hi> and Bay of <hi>Cales,</hi> but could not heare that the Gallions had put in ther, for wee were reſolued to ſet vpon thoſe Gallyons that lay within that Bay: But the ſame day hauing otherwiſe determined wee ſailed for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes to the ſtraights of <hi>Gibraltar</hi> intending to finde out thoſe Gallions or Spaniſh Nauie and to aſſaile them. Vpon the 25 of Aprill com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming before the towne of <hi>Tangier</hi> vpon the coaſt of <hi>Barbary</hi> lying in the mouth of the ſtraights, and finding the Gallions not there, the Admiral ſent for his Counſell abourd his ſhippe, where it was reſolutely determined, that if the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Nauie were in the Bay of <hi>Gibraltar</hi> they
<pb facs="tcp:16806:3"/>
would ſet vpon them, although it were in their owne hauen and vnder ſhot both of the towne and Caſtle, and to end wee tooke order in what ſort to aſſaile them, which was firſt our Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall with Captaine <hi>Lambert Hindrickſon</hi> of <hi>Rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terdam</hi> being Rereadmirall ſhould ſet vpon and bourd the Spaniſh Admirall and our Vice Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall and Captaine <hi>Bras</hi> of <hi>Horne</hi> ſhould fight with the Spaniſh Vice Admirall and ſo euery one in order: At laſt comming to the Bay of <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bralter</hi> and finding the Spaniſh army there, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently wee began with Gods helpe to proceede in our reſolution in ſuch order as time and place required, where wee found 21. ſhippes amongſt which were ſome Frenchmen <hi>Emdeners</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Merchants ſhippes, vpon our approach the Spaniſh Admira'l wayed Anchor and went neerer the town and lay by foure other Gallions but the Vice admiral lay ſtil hauing a bourd 450. men, as the priſoners after certified vs, the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall had 100. Caueliers out of the towne that voluntarily came abourd to help him although hee was well prouided of men before, all this notwithſtanding and although he had th'aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of th'ordnance of the towne and caſtels yet our Admirall and Captaine <hi>Lambert</hi> of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terdam</hi> valiantly bourded him, and the reſt of our ſhips aſwell as they could ſet vpon the reſt of the Gallions, and alſo vpon the Spaniſh Vice
<pb facs="tcp:16806:4"/>
Admirall; And after wee had fought in that moſt furious aſſault both with ordinance and forceable bourding their Ships 4 howers or thereabouts by Gods helpe we got the victory, all the Gallions being ſpoiled batterd and burnt were driue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on ground &amp; amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt the reſt the Admi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ral of 800 tonns, called S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> wherin the generall called <hi>Don Iohn Alveres Dauila</hi> borne in <hi>Aſtorga</hi> was ſlaine, beeing an olde experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Souldiour that had ſerued at Sea in <hi>Don Iohn de Auſtria</hi> his time, alſo the Vice Admirall was ſlaine and the Coronell of the Souldiors and all the Captaines of their Nauie, the Galli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and the reſt of the Spaniſh ſhips were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently burnt downe to the water, whereof two did driue on ſhore but ſo ſpoyled that they were altogether vnſeruiceable, thi'n ſignes, ſtreamers and pendants of the Admiral, Vice Admirall and other Gallions we tooke with vs and ſome other pillage, but by reaſon of the terrible fyer in the Spaniſh Vice Admirall and other Galli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that were on fire and ranne on ground wee could not bring any Ships or Ordnance away, for we were in great daunger of fire our ſelues, &amp; diuers of vs had work enough to do to quench the fire that had gotten into the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but God of his mercie preſerued vs. Of all the men in the Spaniſh armie but fewe eſcaped, for the Bond of <hi>Gibralter</hi> ſhewed as if it had bin ſowed with
<pb facs="tcp:16806:4"/>
Spaniards that leapt ouer-boord, &amp; thoſe that we took confeſſed that they were 4000. men in the Nauie. We tooke 50. priſoners, one where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of was the Generalls ſonne called <hi>Iohn Alueres Dauila</hi> Captaine of the Gallion called S Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine. In this fight we loſt our valiant Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall <hi>Iacob Van Hemſterk,</hi> who with an hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and braue reſolution vndertooke this fight and with the aide of the Vice Admirall Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Lambert of <hi>Rotterdam,</hi> and Captaine <hi>Peter Williamſon</hi> brauely ouercame &amp; by gods helpe vanquiſhed there enemie. The 26. of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prill we brought our ſhips from before the town and caſtell, for with their continual ſhooting they did vs much hurt, and being without their reach wee manned out ſome of our boates and ſente, them to the burnt ſhips which lay vpon the ſhore, which the ſpaniards on land perceiuing wente themſelues to ſet thadmiralls ſhip on fire, which lay all ſhotte and torne vpon the ſtrande, and ſo they did that which we ment to haue doon. In this fight there was at leaſt 8000. greate ſhotte diſcharged and was hardily &amp; furiouſly fought, being fearefull and terrible to behould when the ſpaniſh gallions began to burne, eſpecially when fire came to their powder, it ſhewed as if newe clouds and lightning had riſen out of the ſea and mounted into the skie by a ſailer called <hi>Gouert</hi> an Engliſh man but gaue himſelfe out for one of
<pb facs="tcp:16806:5"/>
               <hi>Embden,</hi> that was taken priſoner by the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh general and ſet at liberty vpon our approach to bee aduiſed and counſelled by him what were beſt to bee don: wee were aduertiſed that the Admirall would not beleeue wee durſt be ſo bold to bourd him in the Kings Bay or hauen, and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially vnder the ſhot of the towne and Caſtle of <hi>Gibraltar,</hi> which contrary to their expectation wee made them feele. The Spaniſh Generall had certaine aduice before of our comming how many ſhippes of warre wee had and with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant ſhippes and Souldiours. Amongſt other thinges that wee tooke wee found the Kinges ſecret inſtructions ſigned with the King of Spaines owne hand <hi>Ioel Rey</hi> whereby we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue what vnaccuſtomed tyranny the ſaid King had commaunded him to execute and to torment the naturall borne inhabitantes of the nether lands eſpecially the Hollanders and Zelanders and all their adherents, ſo that other nations by this comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſion were not altogether exempted. The 27. of Aprill wee ſet ſaile and put out of the bay of Gibraltar, and made toward the coaſt of Barbary, firſt going to Chuta and entered ſo far into that bay that they ſhotte at vs both from the towne and other places of the ſhore, there the Portugalles in great numbers gott vppon their horſes, fearing to bee dealt withall as they were at Gibraltar: but becauſe of the vnfitnes and bad
<pb facs="tcp:16806:5"/>
ſecurity of the place, we ſayled further to the bay of Titnan five Miles from Chuta to rigge our ſhips for that many of them were vnfurniſhed of Boreſprits, Maſts, Sailes, Cordage and other things, and had beene ſhotte through and fired in bourding the Spaniſh Gallions: and comming beefore <hi>Titnan</hi> (a place vnder the Turks and Moores commaund) wee were very welcome vnto them; and vpon the 28. of April the gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor with many Turkiſh ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tlemen came abourd our ſhips bidding vs welcome offering vs all fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and friendſhip hee could aforde vs, and to aide vs withall wee ſtoode in neede off for our wounded men or otherwiſe: hee and all his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany and country ſeeming to bee glad of the vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory which (by Gods helpe) we had obtained a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Spaniards. The fourth of May at <hi>Titnan</hi> ſixe miles from <hi>Chuta</hi> vpon the coaſt of <hi>Barbary</hi> wee new rigged and prepared our ſhips (which were ſore battred) of all neceſſaries, ſtaying Gods pleaſure for an Eaſterly winde to paſſe the ſtraights, and once againe to ſeeke after our enemies, deuiding our Fleet into foure ſquadrons, the Admirall beeing accompanied with ſeuen other ſhippes of warre and the like in euery ſquadron. The Admirall Mounſieur <hi>Hemſterk</hi> that was ſlaine was a very wiſe and well experienced man, who with greate paine, labour and induſtry had beene twice in the could
<pb facs="tcp:16806:6"/>
Streights of <hi>Weygattes,</hi> and at the Eaſt <hi>Indies,</hi> where in his laſt voyage he ouercame and took the great rich Carackts comming from <hi>Malacho</hi> in <hi>China,</hi> with whome of good will and affection toward him many men ventured their liues in this voyage, as amongſt others <hi>Ioris Van Spil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg</hi> that hath beene both in the Eaſt and Weſt <hi>Indies</hi> and imployed in this Fleete as Commiſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and one of the Counſell of warre, generall captaine of the Zeland Souldiers, and diuerſe other captaines.</p>
            <div type="enclosed_list">
               <list>
                  <head>THE <hi>Names of the ſpaniſh Gallions that</hi> were ſpoiled and burnt with many <hi>others, wherof the names are not known.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <item>The Admirall S Auguſtine</item>
                  <item>The vice-admirall noſtra Seniora de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la vera</item>
                  <item>The reare admirall noſtra Seniora ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dre de dios</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16806:6"/>The S Anna</item>
                  <item>Noſtra Seniora de la Regla</item>
                  <item>Noſtra Seniora de conception</item>
                  <item>The S Chriſtopher</item>
                  <item>Noſtra Seniora de los dolores</item>
                  <item>The S Michael</item>
                  <item>Nostra Seniora del Roſario</item>
                  <item>Noſtra Seniora de lo O</item>
                  <item>The S Peter</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours to command. <hi>I.V.S.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
